<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[toptable Tech Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://tech.toptable.co.uk/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://tech.toptable.co.uk/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-05T13:42:17+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://tech.toptable.co.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[toptable]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using Vagrant to work with ElasticSearch on your local machine]]></title>
    <link href="http://tech.toptable.co.uk/blog/2013/08/05/using-vagrant-to-work-with-elasticsearch-on-your-local-machine/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-05T08:45:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://tech.toptable.co.uk/blog/2013/08/05/using-vagrant-to-work-with-elasticsearch-on-your-local-machine</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently, I have started to work a lot more with <a href="http://www.vagrantup.com/">Vagrant</a> as a tool for creating a standard development environment across my team. This essentially means that regardless what the developers&#8217; machine is set up or running as, they can still reproduce the same environment as their colleagues just by entering a command.</p>

<p>Configuration managgement is something we have had to embrace to help us maintain an ever changing world of technologies. The hardest thing is knowing what we actually have to build in these environments. We use Vagrant to help us understand this. The simple flow is as follows:</p>

<ul>
<li>Developer starts a new project</li>
<li>Developer creates a Vagrantfile to spin up a local VM</li>
<li>Vagrantfile gets iterated on as the development process goes forward</li>
</ul>


<p>Once the developer understands what they need to actually run their software, we would then go about creating an environment to which this software will actually be deployed for end-to-end testing. I won&#8217;t go any further into the details of our Vagrant flow in this post, if you want to read more about how to get started with Vagrant, then I would suggest reading <a href="http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920026358.do">Vagrant Up and Running</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/mitchellh">Mitchell Hashimoto</a>.</p>

<h2>Vagrant and ElasticSearch</h2>

<p>Whilst reviewing a book on <a href="http://www.elasticsearch.org/">ElasticSearch</a>, I noticed how simple the instructions were to get up and running with ElasticSearch. Please note, that there are already lots of Puppet modules for configuring ElasticSearch on <a href="http://forge.puppetlabs.com/modules?q=elasticsearch">Puppetlabs Forge</a>. This post only talks about how I was able to quickly spin up some local instances. I didn&#8217;t want to manually do this, so I decided to use Vagrant (and Puppet) to take care of it for me. The instructions can be summarised as follows:</p>

<ul>
<li>Download and install the JavaSDK</li>
<li>Download the specific ElasticSearch package</li>
<li>Install ElasticSearch</li>
<li>Download and install curl (to be able to interact with ElasticSearch)</li>
<li>Make sure the service is started</li>
</ul>


<p>I hate doing this manually. Luckily, with the correct script, I am able to automate all of this as follows:</p>

<pre><code>Vagrant.configure("2") do |config|
    config.vm.box = "Ubuntu precise 64 VMWare"
    config.vm.box_url = "http://files.vagrantup.com/precise64_vmware.box"
    config.vm.network :forwarded_port, guest: 9200, host: 9200
    config.vm.provision :puppet do |puppet|
        puppet.module_path = '../setup/modules'
        puppet.manifests_path = '../setup/manifests'
        puppet.manifest_file = 'default.pp'
        puppet.options = '--verbose --debug'
    end
end
</code></pre>

<p>Essentially, this script says to create a clone of a VM from a predefined box, forward port 9200 on the vm to 9200 on my local machine and then provision the server using Puppet. The Puppet script works as follows:</p>

<pre><code>exec { "apt-get-update":
    command =&gt; "/usr/bin/apt-get update",
}

package {'curl':
    provider =&gt; apt,
    ensure   =&gt; latest,
    require  =&gt; Exec['apt-get-update']
}

class {'elasticsearch':
    version =&gt; '0.90.0',
    require =&gt; Exec['apt-get-update'],
}
</code></pre>

<p>This defines that the command apt-get-update gets applied (due to both the class and the package requiring it) and then will install curl and ElasticSearch in no particular order. Once the script runs, I will be able to open a browser on my local machine, go to http://localhost:9200 and see the newly provisioned ElasticSearch node. The result of the JSON was something similar to this:</p>

<pre><code>{
    "ok" : true,
    "status" : 200,
    "name" : "Gibborim",
    "version" : {
        "number" : "0.90.0",
        "snapshot_build" : false,
    },
    "tagline" : "You Know, for Search"
}
</code></pre>

<p>By entering the URL, &#8217;<strong>http://localhost:9200/_cluster/health?pretty</strong>&#8217;, you can see the state of the ElasticSearch cluster. It should show something like this:</p>

<pre><code>{
    "cluster_name" : "elasticsearch",
    "status" : "yellow",
    "timed_out" : false,
    "number_of_nodes" : 1,              
    "number_of_data_nodes" : 1,         
    "active_primary_shards" : 5,        
    "active_shards" : 5,                
    "relocating_shards" : 0,            
    "initializing_shards" : 0,          
    "unassigned_shards" : 5             
}
</code></pre>

<p>I wanted to be able to provision multiple nodes and then let them create a cluster. I was able to take the existing Vagrantfile and then using the multi-environment features of Vagrant. This created a new Vagrantfile as follows:</p>

<pre><code>Vagrant::Config.run do |config|
    config.vm.box = "Ubuntu precise 64 VMWare"
    config.vm.box_url = "http://files.vagrantup.com/precise64_vmware.box"

    config.vm.define "es1" do |es1|
        es1.vm.network :hostonly, "192.168.1.10"
        es1.vm.provision :puppet do |puppet|
            puppet.module_path = '../setup/modules'
            puppet.manifests_path = '../setup/manifests'
            puppet.manifest_file = 'default.pp'
            puppet.options = '--verbose --debug'
        end
    end

    config.vm.define "es2" do |es2|
        es2.vm.network :hostonly, "192.168.1.11"
        es2.vm.provision :puppet do |puppet|
            puppet.module_path = '../setup/modules'
            puppet.manifests_path = '../setup/manifests'
            puppet.manifest_file = 'default.pp'
            puppet.options = '--verbose --debug'
        end
    end

    config.vm.define "es3" do |es3|
        es3.vm.network :hostonly, "192.168.1.12"
        es3.vm.provision :puppet do |puppet|
            puppet.module_path = '../setup/modules'
            puppet.manifests_path = '../setup/manifests'
            puppet.manifest_file = 'default.pp'
            puppet.options = '--verbose --debug'
        end
    end
end
</code></pre>

<p>This effectively tells Vagrant to create three instances of ElasticSearch using the Puppet configuration (as above). Each ElasticSearch node is given its own IP. Thanks to ElasticSearch using Multicast and Unicast discovery, it is able to find other nodes on the network and create a cluster. By running a similar url as before, &#8217;<strong>http://192.168.1.10:9200/_cluster/health?pretty</strong>&#8217;, we can now see that the cluster looks as follows:</p>

<pre><code>{
    "cluster_name" : "elasticsearch",
    "status" : "green",
    "timed_out" : false,
    "number_of_nodes" : 3,              
    "number_of_data_nodes" : 3,         
    "active_primary_shards" : 5,        
    "active_shards" : 15,                
    "relocating_shards" : 0,            
    "initializing_shards" : 0,          
    "unassigned_shards" : 0             
}
</code></pre>

<p>Using this method, we can continue to spin up as many instances as we need to replicate different scenarios or testing conditions. Vagrant has made this very easy to do. If you want a copy of the Vagrantfiles and Puppet modules to try this yourself, then you can find them on my <a href="https://github.com/stack72/vagrant-examples/tree/master/elasticsearch">github repository</a>. The scripts are available under the <a href="http://opensource.org/licenses/MIT">MIT</a> license.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[One Gun - Many Enemies]]></title>
    <link href="http://tech.toptable.co.uk/blog/2013/07/24/one-gun-many-enemies/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-24T14:32:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://tech.toptable.co.uk/blog/2013/07/24/one-gun-many-enemies</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I spent some time, re-investigating Javascript. After a few months of intensive TDD and SOLID training at OpenTable I was curious how those principles apply in a slightly different environment. Guess what, they do not differ that much&#8230; I planned to write about all this sometime in the future after gaining more experience from real battles ahead, however <a href="http://watirmelon.com/2013/02/09/why-i-dont-like-Jasmine/">Watirmelon post</a> invited me to attack this subject immediately.</p>

<p>I went through the available testing frameworks for Javascript and decided on Jasmine. Why? Mainly because of its BDD syntax which is fashionable this season. The second reason is that it has really cool documentation. Finally, the basic set up of just running an HTML file in a browser got me up and running fast.</p>

<p>Let&#8217;s look at the basics - what I expect from different types of tests and how Jasmine fits into those requirements:</p>

<h2>Unit Testing</h2>

<h3>Advice from senior craftsman</h3>

<ul>
<li>Shoot them one by one
(structure your code so that it is easier to maintain)</li>
<li>Be sure you kill with every shot
(verify small bits of code to nail down issues)</li>
<li>Kill them all
(verify edge cases)</li>
<li>Kill them quick
(provide fast feedback on issues)</li>
<li>Choose a fast shooting gun - the faster you shoot, the more enemies you will kill
(unit tests must be blazing fast)</li>
<li>Choose the most reliable gun - if it is stuck then you are dead
(when unit tests are brittle you will stop depending on them)</li>
<li>Your gun needs to be light enough to carry everywhere
(unit tests are your gun, so you must be able to run them all locally)</li>
</ul>


<p>Jasmine works great for all those aims, as it is really fast and it allows you to stub both objects and DOM elements (especially combined with a Jasmine-jQuery plugin). Keep in mind that Unit Testing is useful only if you either write new code or refactor old code. Do not ever try to write Unit Tests for existing code which you don&#8217;t intend to refactor. It&#8217;s like shooting the dead. You simply cannot kill them with another bullet.</p>

<h2>Integration Testing</h2>

<h3>Advice from senior craftsman</h3>

<ul>
<li>Beware of the hidden sniper
(test against external dependencies like files, databases, network services)</li>
<li>You are part of your squad
(verify that components of the application work well together)</li>
<li>Observe the environment
(try to use depenedencies as close to the real problem as possible e.g. example file, database with test data, test version of an external service)</li>
<li>Point in the right direction
(do not try to test your stack top-down, instead concentrate on interfaces and adapters that you could not test in unit tests)</li>
</ul>


<p>Integration tests will naturally be harder to quickly setup - they might break due to configuration problems or inaccessible external services. That&#8217;s why you don&#8217;t want to have that many of them. Still, you want to know that all your problems are due to your partner changing protocol. Once again nothing stops us from using Jasmine here.</p>

<p>Jasmine just executes your tests, so the tests that point towards external services, send example files to your code etc. will all be a breeze to implement with Jasmine.</p>

<h2>Acceptance Testing</h2>

<h3>Aims</h3>

<ul>
<li>Confirm you are fighting the right war
(show specification to your product owner/manager/client)</li>
<li>Keep clean supply routes
(test the functionality of your app with full set up and all dependencies)</li>
<li>Find hidden mines
(test your application in all environments to which you deploy)</li>
</ul>


<h3>Advice from senior craftsman</h3>

<ul>
<li>Speak in their language
(use a tool which allows writing tests in natural language such as Cucumber or SpecFlow)</li>
<li>Take your time
(those tests will be slower, so accept that you will not always run them locally and that you will not run them every minute)</li>
<li>Spend your resources wisely
(acceptance tests are naturally much more brittle then other types of tests, so try to keep their number reasonably small)</li>
</ul>


<p>This is where I would not recommend Jasmine, simply because it doesn&#8217;t fit this job. Its syntax is based on programming language, so it is harder to read by non-engineers. Jasmine allows you to execute events and call your code. However, your users will be most likely be using a browser to interact with your code, so it is much better to use a tool that also uses a browser to test your web page.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>I find Jasmine extremely well suited for unit and integration testing. I wouldn&#8217;t use it for acceptance tests as there are quite few better tools for that job. And I guess that is the issue that Alister Scott has with Jasmine on his blog - he tried to use it for acceptance testing. In that case I wouldn&#8217;t choose Jasmine either. On the other hand I don&#8217;t like using a screwdriver to hammer a nail.</p>

<h2>Post Scriptum (on DOM dependency)</h2>

<p>Alister also complains about integration issues between his server-side code and client-side code. His experience is that changes to IDs and classes in MVC applications result in failing Javascript. The issue is serious and shows one important mistake, which is hardcoding dependencies. IDs and class names are configurable details and Javascript code should be agnostic of them. To illustrate let&#8217;s look at a simple test case from my pet-project:</p>

<pre><code>describe("GameController", function(){
  describe("During Initialize", function() {
    var view;
    var subject;

    beforeEach(function() {    
        setFixtures("&lt;div id="myid"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;");
        subject = new GameView();

        subject.CreateFabricInDiv("#myid");
    });

    it("creates fabric in div", function(){
        expect($("#myid")).not.toBeEmpty();
    });

    it("holds pointer to canvas", function(){
        expect(subject._canvas).not.toBe(undefined);
    });
 }); 
</code></pre>

<p>Do you see how &#8220;#myid&#8221; parameter is passed into the method call? We moved the configuration detail out from the Javascript code, which in my opinion it is the simplest solution to Alister&#8217;s problem.</p>

<p>If code is designed in such a way that IDs/class names are not embedded all around the codebase you can figure out quite few nice ways to keep them consistent between Javascript and server-side code.</p>

<p>It also helps with code re-usability as you can use the same code on two separate pages with differing IDs!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Managing Windows Certificates with PowerShell]]></title>
    <link href="http://tech.toptable.co.uk/blog/2013/07/08/managing-windows-certificates-with-powershell/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-08T18:51:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://tech.toptable.co.uk/blog/2013/07/08/managing-windows-certificates-with-powershell</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Managing certificates on Windows is <em>really</em> painful. There is no easy way to do it. The general way to install a certificate to a Windows Server 2008 machine is as follows:</p>

<ul>
<li>Open the Certificates snap-in for a user, computer, or service.</li>
<li>In the console tree, click the logical store where you want to import the certificate.</li>
<li>On the Action menu, point to All Tasks, and then click Import to start the Certificate Import Wizard.</li>
<li>Type the file name containing the certificate to be imported.</li>
<li>If you want to specify where the certificate is stored, select Place all certificates in the following store, click Browse, and choose the certificate store to use. OR</li>
<li>If the certificate should be automatically placed in a certificate store based on the type of certificate, click Automatically select the certificate store based on the type of certificate.</li>
</ul>


<p>The first time I ran this process, I felt as though this was just wrong to not be able to automate. The goal of our team is to automate everything we are currently doing manually. PowerShell is a better option for this import process as it allows you to write code to do it. As we all know, code is better for a number of reasons, I won&#8217;t go into the infrastructure as code argument in this post (but it is coming soon….). Using PowerShell, I can write a simple function as follows:</p>

<pre><code>function Import-PfxCertificate($certName, $CertLocaton, $certRootStore, $certStore) {    
     $pfx = new-object System.Security.Cryptography.X509Certificates.X509Certificate2    

     $pfxPass = convertto-securestring $CertPassword -asplaintext -force

     $certPath = $CertLocaton + "\" + $certName   
     $pfx.import($certPath,$pfxPass,"Exportable,PersistKeySet")    

     $store = new-object System.Security.Cryptography.X509Certificates.X509Store($certStore,$certRootStore)    
     $store.open("MaxAllowed")    
     $store.add($pfx)    
     $store.close()    
}
</code></pre>

<p>This makes certificate management easier. To manage certificates in this way, I just need to invoke a script similar to this:</p>

<pre><code>.\import-certificate.ps1 -CertificateName "mycert.pfx" -CertLocation "c:\ssl\mycerts"
</code></pre>

<p>Much simpler! You can download a <a href="https://gist.github.com/opentable-devops/5951108">gist</a> of this script should you wish to use it. Please note that the license that this script is available under can be read from our <a href="https://github.com/opentable/licensing/blob/master/LICENSE">github repository</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[NDC Oslo]]></title>
    <link href="http://tech.toptable.co.uk/blog/2013/06/18/ndcoslo/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-18T11:59:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://tech.toptable.co.uk/blog/2013/06/18/ndcoslo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Three toptable heroes took to Norway last week to attend NDC Oslo. For two of us it was our first major conference and for one, Paul Stack, he had to speak.</p>

<p>Personally, as my first large, multi-discipline conference, I didn&#8217;t really know what to expect. Being away from the team for three days in a foreign country with major project work going on at the same time was a bit uncomfortable. I was worried that the time and expense needed to be justified. That fear went away after the first night in the bar!</p>

<p>The sessions were great, many things I haven&#8217;t had a chance to investigate were covered, things like Functional Programming, the latest JavaScript frameworks and tooling. There were also sessions covering things I am more involved with, Agile Process, SOA &amp; Rest, Team Structure and Hiring.</p>

<p>There are other posts around about the individual sessions but I am now much more enthusiastic about functional programming particularly how we could use it and getting back into front end development (even if just in my own time).</p>

<p>The main thing I enjoyed and learnt though is meeting the other delegates. I think staying away from home makes this much more prevalent, something to consider for other conferences. Meeting people at all levels or experience and especially the speakers, most of whom are very generous with their time and ideas, teaches you the most. I probably learnt more over the shuffle board of The Dubliner Pub than reading blog post online in a year (that may be a stretch, but I did learn I was by far the best player on the night).</p>

<p>Watching a colleague speak was also interesting, when you work with a buffoon, however passionate and hard working, to see people actually interested in what he has to say is an eye opener. It makes you realise what you are doing and all its challenges are a step forwards and one to keep pursuing. It also makes you think, &#8220;if he can do it, I must be able to, what knowledge should I share?&#8221;. What to share is the hard bit.</p>

<p>My final point is how often I should try to get to these; one a year for sure, any more than that? I need to think that through.</p>

<p>Thanks to the organisers of the conference for a well organised, varied and enjoyable time. And if you have project work on, the wifi was excellent so you need never be too far away from the rest of the team, just do it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Windows Feature Management with PowerShell]]></title>
    <link href="http://tech.toptable.co.uk/blog/2013/06/14/windows-feature-management-with-powershell/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-14T20:31:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://tech.toptable.co.uk/blog/2013/06/14/windows-feature-management-with-powershell</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In late 2012, our development team started to move towards our systems being much more automated. Long gone are the days of developers creating runbooks in Word and giving them to our operations team to use to set up our production servers.</p>

<p>When building our webservers on Windows, in order to install / activate Windows features, this was the general set of instructions that was needed to be followed:</p>

<ul>
<li>Click Start Button</li>
<li>Click on Control Panel</li>
<li>Click on Programs</li>
<li>Click on Turn Windows features on or off</li>
</ul>


<p>This would present a screen as follows:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://tech.toptable.co.uk/images/posts/windowsfeature.png"></p>

<p>You would need to find the correct features to enable and check the box, press OK and then wait for the features to be installed.</p>

<p>When Microsoft introduced Windows Server 2008 and PowerShell 2.0, they also introducted the module &#8216;ServerManager&#8217;. This is a module that allows us to interact, with PowerShell, Windows Features using a range of cmdlets:</p>

<ul>
<li>Get-WindowsFeature</li>
<li>Add-WindowsFeature</li>
<li>Remove-WindowsFeature</li>
</ul>


<p>This meant that instead of creating runbooks in Word, our developers could create automation scripts that would take a base Windows Server 2008 server and enable all the Windows Features needed to run our applications. This allowed our operations team to move much faster in configuring our servers.</p>

<p>To turn on the ASP.NET Application Development features in Windows, we would run the following script from PowerShell:</p>

<pre><code>Import-Module ServerManager
Add-WindowsFeature Web-Asp-Net
</code></pre>

<p>By knowing what Windows Features we needed to install on our servers, we were able to create the following script:</p>

<pre><code>function enable_net_3_5_features()
{
    Add-WindowsFeature NET-HTTP-Activation
    Add-WindowsFeature NET-Win-CFAC
    Add-WindowsFeature NET-Non-HTTP-Activ
    Add-WindowsFeature AS-MSMQ-Activation
}

function enable_iis_common_http_features()
{
    Add-WindowsFeature Web-Static-Content
    Add-WindowsFeature Web-Http-Errors
    Add-WindowsFeature Web-Default-Doc
}

function enable_iis_application_development_features()
{
    Add-WindowsFeature Web-Asp-Net
    Add-WindowsFeature Web-Net-Ext
    Add-WindowsFeature Web-ISAPI-Ext
    Add-WindowsFeature Web-ISAPI-Filter
}

function enable_iis_health_and_diagnostics_features()
{
    Add-WindowsFeature Web-Http-Logging
    Add-WindowsFeature Web-Request-Monitor
}

function enable_iis_security_features()
{
    Add-WindowsFeature Web-Filtering
}

function enable_iis_performance_features()
{
    Add-WindowsFeature Web-Stat-Compression
    Add-WindowsFeature Web-Dyn-Compression
}

function enable_iis_management_tools()
{
    Add-WindowsFeature Web-Mgmt-Tools
    Add-WindowsFeature Web-Mgmt-Console
}


Write-Host('Starting Application Server Setup')

Import-Module ServerManager
enable_net_3_5_features
enable_iis_common_http_features
enable_iis_application_development_features
enable_iis_health_and_diagnostics_features
enable_iis_security_features
enable_iis_performance_features
enable_iis_management_tools 

Write-Host('Application Server Setup complete')
</code></pre>

<p>Running the script, meant that we could enable features much faster than we could enable them via the GUI. Notice how we have grouped how we enable Windows Features into the same groupings found in the &#8216;Turn Windows features on or off&#8217; menu. For a full list of the names of the features that can be turned on or off, please refer to this <a href="http://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc732757.aspx">technet article</a></p>

<p>You can download a <a href="https://gist.github.com/opentable-devops/5886831">gist</a> of this script if you want to use it. Please note that the license that this script is available under can be read from our <a href="https://github.com/opentable/licensing/blob/master/LICENSE">github repository</a>. We hope that the script helps you as much as it helped us.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[nLocalGeoCoder]]></title>
    <link href="http://tech.toptable.co.uk/blog/2013/06/07/nlocalgeocoder/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-07T11:59:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://tech.toptable.co.uk/blog/2013/06/07/nlocalgeocoder</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>History</h2>

<p>With OpenTable having engineering teams spread across multiple offices it&#8217;s important for us to maintain open email dialogue about new products us or our teams have created, new tools we&#8217;ve discovered or problem solving approaches that have helped us achieve our goals.  Recently in one of these emails Aish introduced the team to a new open source ruby implementation of reverse geocode lookup for latitude and longitude he&#8217;d written called <a href="https://github.com/aishfenton/local-geocoder">local-geocoder</a>.  With an interest in understanding how this worked, to learn a bit of ruby, to make this project accessible to .net developers and just to see how long it would take I decided to port it to C# and .net.</p>

<h2>How reverse geocoding works</h2>

<p>Latitude and longitude geographical coordinates are great but 37.819548,-122.479046 doesn&#8217;t really mean much to me. Knowing this is in the San Francisco bay area is much more useful interpretation.</p>

<p>That&#8217;s where reverse geocoding comes in.  Normally geocoding tries to locate geographical coordinates from other data like postal (zip) codes or street level addresses.  Reverse geocoding does the opposite and can, given enough lookup data, be very precise.</p>

<p>There are a number of online reverse geocoding providers, like Google, who can perform this for you however there are normally usage limits or costs for using them.  To add to this the latency of these service can slow your logic down.  Wouldn&#8217;t it be nice if this could be done locally at high speed and in memory.</p>

<h2>Using nLocalGeocoder</h2>

<p>It&#8217;s really easy to use, just new up a Geocoder and you&#8217;re off&#8230;</p>

<pre><code>var geocoder = new Geocoder();
var result = geocoder.ReverseGeocode(-122.479046M, 37.819548M);
</code></pre>

<p>The result variable now holds an instance of the Result struct.  This type has the following properties:-</p>

<ul>
<li>Country <em>- Id and Name of the country</em></li>
</ul>


<p>and for USA only (because that&#8217;s all the data in our <a href="http://www.geojson.org">GeoJSON</a> data)</p>

<ul>
<li>AdministrativeArea1 <em>- Id and Name of the state</em></li>
<li>AdministrativeArea2 <em>- Id and Name of the county</em></li>
</ul>


<p>The code is available for all to use and is available on our <a href="https://github.com/opentable/nLocalGeocoder">github repo</a></p>

<p>It&#8217;s as simple as that really!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting Started With SpecRun]]></title>
    <link href="http://tech.toptable.co.uk/blog/2013/06/07/getting-started-with-specrun/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-07T11:33:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://tech.toptable.co.uk/blog/2013/06/07/getting-started-with-specrun</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>First some background</h2>

<p>We recently switched from writing automated acceptance from Cucumber to SpecFlow&#8230; this is no slight on Cucumber it&#8217;s just that we had a lot of C# developers who wanted to get closer to writing acceptance tests. Worth adding that SpecFlow has also come a long way as a .Net port of Cucumber and is pretty much like for like now.</p>

<h2>Why should I bother with SpecRun?</h2>

<p>Initially we ran our entire unit, integration and acceptance tests via nUnit. Pretty much industry standard but we felt nUnit wasn&#8217;t really a good tool to run acceptance tests - yes it&#8217;ll do the job but we were looking for better performance, quicker failure feedback and more comprehensive reporting. If you want details on SpecRun vs. nUnit Gasper has a <a href="http://gasparnagy.com/2011/09/specrun-because-integration-tests-are-not-unit-tests/">great blog post</a>.</p>

<p><salespitch>SpecRun itself is free to use although there is a random delay when running acceptance locally, setting up SpecRun on a CI environment is totally free and does not include the same delay. Definitely worth trying out and you can purchase a licence later if you like what it offers.</salespitch></p>

<h2>Installing SpecRun</h2>

<p>If you are already using SpecFlow with nUnit the migration to SpecRun is really simple - <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=c2ge90BWeI0">this video</a> shows you how to setup the test runner but I found myself having to watch it too many times. This post is an attempt at recording the steps should we roll out SpecRun for another project.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m assuming you&#8217;re running Visual Studio and are familiar with Nuget packages. I&#8217;ll break it down so I don&#8217;t miss anything:</p>

<ol>
<li>In VS, select your Acceptance test project and get the Nuget package down for SpecRun: <code>install-package SpecRun</code>.</li>
<li>You&#8217;ll notice Nuget automatically adds configuration to your app.config so it&#8217;s safe to remove the nUnit provider setting (this is to enable you to pick and choose your test runner but we prefer to only use SpecRun).</li>
<li>Open the Default.srprofile file and we normally delete any commented settings here.</li>
<li>Still inside Default.srprofile add the properties for projectName and projectId. The projectName is what you see in VS the projectId can be found by opening the acceptance .proj file and taking the projectGuid.</li>
<li>Setup the execution properties - this really depends on what you want to get out of running the tool - what retry count you want, whether to run on multiple threads, etc. Here are the values we normally use:</li>
</ol>


<p><code>&lt;Execution retryFor="None" stopAfterFailures="100" testThreadCount="1" testSchedulingMode="Sequential" apartmentState="STA"/&gt;</code></p>

<ol>
<li>We did tweak the SpecRun .cmd file used to run acceptance via command line - <a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/8835075/runacceptance.cmd">copy this file</a> to your project root, you may need to tweak some names and paths.</li>
</ol>


<p>Once you&#8217;ve gone through those steps you should be able to browse to your project root, type <strong>runacceptance.cmd tag_to_run</strong> and it&#8217;ll run your acceptance tests tagged <strong>@tag_to_run</strong>  (NOTE: you don&#8217;t need to specify the @ symbol).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
