<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: PowerShell | toptable Tech Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://tech.toptable.co.uk/blog/categories/powershell/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://tech.toptable.co.uk/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-24T15:49:08+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://tech.toptable.co.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[toptable]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Managing Windows Certificates with PowerShell]]></title>
    <link href="http://tech.toptable.co.uk/blog/2013/07/08/managing-windows-certificates-with-powershell/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-08T18:51:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://tech.toptable.co.uk/blog/2013/07/08/managing-windows-certificates-with-powershell</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Managing certificates on Windows is <em>really</em> painful. There is no easy way to do it. The general way to install a certificate to a Windows Server 2008 machine is as follows:</p>

<ul>
<li>Open the Certificates snap-in for a user, computer, or service.</li>
<li>In the console tree, click the logical store where you want to import the certificate.</li>
<li>On the Action menu, point to All Tasks, and then click Import to start the Certificate Import Wizard.</li>
<li>Type the file name containing the certificate to be imported.</li>
<li>If you want to specify where the certificate is stored, select Place all certificates in the following store, click Browse, and choose the certificate store to use. OR</li>
<li>If the certificate should be automatically placed in a certificate store based on the type of certificate, click Automatically select the certificate store based on the type of certificate.</li>
</ul>


<p>The first time I ran this process, I felt as though this was just wrong to not be able to automate. The goal of our team is to automate everything we are currently doing manually. PowerShell is a better option for this import process as it allows you to write code to do it. As we all know, code is better for a number of reasons, I won't go into the infrastructure as code argument in this post (but it is coming soon….). Using PowerShell, I can write a simple function as follows:</p>

<pre><code>function Import-PfxCertificate($certName, $CertLocaton, $certRootStore, $certStore) {    
     $pfx = new-object System.Security.Cryptography.X509Certificates.X509Certificate2    

     $pfxPass = convertto-securestring $CertPassword -asplaintext -force

     $certPath = $CertLocaton + "\" + $certName   
     $pfx.import($certPath,$pfxPass,"Exportable,PersistKeySet")    

     $store = new-object System.Security.Cryptography.X509Certificates.X509Store($certStore,$certRootStore)    
     $store.open("MaxAllowed")    
     $store.add($pfx)    
     $store.close()    
}
</code></pre>

<p>This makes certificate management easier. To manage certificates in this way, I just need to invoke a script similar to this:</p>

<pre><code>.\import-certificate.ps1 -CertificateName "mycert.pfx" -CertLocation "c:\ssl\mycerts"
</code></pre>

<p>Much simpler! You can download a <a href="https://gist.github.com/opentable-devops/5951108">gist</a> of this script should you wish to use it. Please note that the license that this script is available under can be read from our <a href="https://github.com/opentable/licensing/blob/master/LICENSE">github repository</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
