<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: PowerShell | OpenTable Tech UK Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://tech.opentable.co.uk/blog/categories/powershell/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://tech.opentable.co.uk/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-22T08:24:57-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://tech.opentable.co.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[OpenTable]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Managing Windows Features with Puppet]]></title>
    <link href="http://tech.opentable.co.uk/blog/2014/05/15/managing-windows-features-with-puppet/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-15T08:12:38-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://tech.opentable.co.uk/blog/2014/05/15/managing-windows-features-with-puppet</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Back in June 2013, I wrote about <a href="http://tech.opentable.co.uk/blog/2013/06/14/windows-feature-management-with-powershell/">Windows Feature Management with PowerShell</a>. We have since released a Puppet module that will do this for us. We originally wrote PowerShell:</p>

<pre><code>Import-Module ServerManager
Add-WindowsFeature Web-Asp-Net
</code></pre>

<p>The Puppet module now wraps this code as follows:</p>

<pre><code>windowsfeature { 'Web-Asp-Net': }
</code></pre>

<p>The declaration windowsfeature is a specific Puppet type called a <a href="http://docs.puppetlabs.com/learning/definedtypes.html">define</a>. In developer terms, this is the equivalent of a helper method that can be reused. We can also make sure that Windows Features are <em>not</em> installed on the server as follows:</p>

<pre><code>windowsfeature { 'Telnet-Server': 
  ensure =&gt; absent 
}
</code></pre>

<p>In the backing code for the module, we do a check before we install / uninstall any windows features. This means that we will only make the changes we really need to. This ensures idempotency of the script. By using this class, we can build up a list of what features a server should have enabled / installed on it. As example manifest would look as follows:</p>

<pre><code>class my_windows_features {
  windowsfeature { 'Web-Asp-Net': }
  windowsfeature { 'Web-Net-Ext': }
  windowsfeature { 'Web-ISAPI-Ext': }
  windowsfeature { 'Web-ISAPI-Filter': }
  windowsfeature { 'Web-Mgmt-Tools': }
  windowsfeature { 'Web-Mgmt-Console': }
  windowsfeature { 'Telnet-Server': ensure =&gt; absent }
}
</code></pre>

<p>The server will have it&rsquo;s shipping list of Windows Features checked every 30 minutes by Puppet. We are sure that any changes encountered during that time will be applied as expected.  You can find more about our WindowsFeature module on the <a href="http://github.com/opentable/puppet-windowsfeature">github repo</a>. If you want to use the module, then you can install it using the Puppet Module tool via the <a href="http://forge.puppetlabs.com/opentable/windowsfeature">Puppet Forge</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Managing Windows Web Applications with Puppet]]></title>
    <link href="http://tech.opentable.co.uk/blog/2014/05/13/managing-windows-web-applications-with-puppet/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-13T07:25:16-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://tech.opentable.co.uk/blog/2014/05/13/managing-windows-web-applications-with-puppet</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As part of our move towards a configuration management tool, we really wanted to start automating as much of our infrastructure as possible. This included our application configuration stack. IIS management is pretty easy with PowerShell. It would look something like this</p>

<pre><code>Import-Module WebAdministration
New-WebSite -Name "DemoSite" -Port 80 -IP * -PhysicalPath "c:\inetpub\wwwroot" -ApplicationPool "MyAppPool"
</code></pre>

<p>This would of course set up a website called &lsquo;DemoSite&rsquo; running on port 80 on the local machine. The cmdlets that come with PowerShell make this pretty easy. This is great if it is a one-off job to set up a site. We run our websites from a number of webservers, therefore, it would be silly to have to RDP into each webserver and run a script on it. This is why tools like Puppet, Chef, Ansible etc. exist. We needed a configuration management tool to do this work for us. It has a number of benefits:</p>

<ul>
<li>Orchestration</li>
<li>Idempotency</li>
<li>Makes sure that each server is configured in &lsquo;exactly&rsquo; the same way as no human intervention is needed</li>
<li>Developers can help the operations team by creating the scripts needed. This is great for collaboration between teams</li>
</ul>


<p>On investigating how we would do this with Puppet, we noticed that there were not many other people managing their site in this way. Therefore, we would have to turn our PowerShell scripts into Puppet modules to manage our system.</p>

<p>We have since created a Puppet module to manage IIS. To manage IIS with Puppet, we can now write the following code:</p>

<pre><code>iis::manage_site { 'DemoSite:
   site_path     =&gt; 'c:\inetpub\wwwroot',
   port          =&gt; '80',
   ip_address    =&gt; '*',
   app_pool      =&gt; 'MyAppPool'
}
</code></pre>

<p>This would produce <strong>exactly</strong> the same results as the code from above. But it has 1 difference. There are checks in the code behind this module that will mean the code will only execute when it is needed, i.e. when the site_path isn&rsquo;t correct or the app_pool isn&rsquo;t correct. This is idempotency. The script can be run again and again and again&hellip;.</p>

<p>To create an application binding, we used to do this in PowerShell:</p>

<pre><code>Import-Module WebAdministration
New-WebBinding -Name 'DemoSite' -Port '8080' -IPAddress '*'
</code></pre>

<p>This would set up an extra binding on port 8080 for the site, DemoSite. We replaced this code with our puppet equivalent:</p>

<pre><code>iis::manage_binding { 'DemoSite-8080':
  site_name   =&gt; 'DemoSite',
  protocol    =&gt; 'http',
  port        =&gt; '8080',
  ip_address  =&gt; '*',
}
</code></pre>

<p>To create a virtual application, we would write the PowerShell:</p>

<pre><code>Import-Module WebAdministration
New-WebApplication -Name 'VirtualApp' -Site 'DemoSite' -PhysicalPath 'c:\inetpub\wwwroot\MyVirtualApp' -ApplicationPool 'MyAppPool'
</code></pre>

<p>This will create a VirtualApp folder on the DemoSite, use the same application pool and then set the path of the folder. I can do the same thing in Puppet as follows:</p>

<pre><code>iis::manage_virtual_application {'VirtualApp':
  site_name   =&gt; 'DemoSite',
  site_path   =&gt; 'C:\inetpub\wwwroot\MyVirtualApplication',
  app_pool    =&gt; 'MyAppPool'
 }  
</code></pre>

<p>We can therefore, chain a manifest together that does all this for us in 1 go. It would look as follows:</p>

<pre><code>class mywebsite {
  iis::manage_app_pool {'MyAppPool':
    enable_32_bit           =&gt; true,
    managed_runtime_version =&gt; 'v4.0',
  } -&gt;

  iis::manage_site {'DemoSite':
    site_path   =&gt; 'C:\inetpub\wwwroot',
    port        =&gt; '80',
    ip_address  =&gt; '*',
    app_pool    =&gt; 'MyAppPool'
  } -&gt;

  iis::manage_virtual_application {'VirtualApp':
    site_name  =&gt; 'DemoSite',
    site_path  =&gt; 'C:\inetpub\wwwroot\MyVirtualApp',
    app_pool   =&gt; 'MyAppPool'
  } -&gt; 

  iis::manage_binding {'DemoSite-8080':
    site_name  =&gt; 'DemoSite',
    protocol   =&gt; 'http',
    port       =&gt; '8080',
    ip_address =&gt; '*'
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>The module does more than just these tasks and I could give more and more examples of what we wrote, but you can find more about our IIS module on the <a href="http://github.com/opentable/puppet-iis">github repo</a>. If you want to use the module, then you can install it using the Puppet Module tool via the <a href="http://forge.puppetlabs.com/opentable/iis">Puppet forge</a>.</p>

<p>We love to hear feedback on things that the module should support. We like Pull Requests even more :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Managing Windows Certificates with PowerShell]]></title>
    <link href="http://tech.opentable.co.uk/blog/2013/07/08/managing-windows-certificates-with-powershell/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-08T18:51:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://tech.opentable.co.uk/blog/2013/07/08/managing-windows-certificates-with-powershell</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Managing certificates on Windows is <em>really</em> painful. There is no easy way to do it. The general way to install a certificate to a Windows Server 2008 machine is as follows:</p>

<ul>
<li>Open the Certificates snap-in for a user, computer, or service.</li>
<li>In the console tree, click the logical store where you want to import the certificate.</li>
<li>On the Action menu, point to All Tasks, and then click Import to start the Certificate Import Wizard.</li>
<li>Type the file name containing the certificate to be imported.</li>
<li>If you want to specify where the certificate is stored, select Place all certificates in the following store, click Browse, and choose the certificate store to use. OR</li>
<li>If the certificate should be automatically placed in a certificate store based on the type of certificate, click Automatically select the certificate store based on the type of certificate.</li>
</ul>


<p>The first time I ran this process, I felt as though this was just wrong to not be able to automate. The goal of our team is to automate everything we are currently doing manually. PowerShell is a better option for this import process as it allows you to write code to do it. As we all know, code is better for a number of reasons, I won&rsquo;t go into the infrastructure as code argument in this post (but it is coming soon….). Using PowerShell, I can write a simple function as follows:</p>

<pre><code>function Import-PfxCertificate($certName, $CertLocaton, $certRootStore, $certStore) {    
     $pfx = new-object System.Security.Cryptography.X509Certificates.X509Certificate2    

     $pfxPass = convertto-securestring $CertPassword -asplaintext -force

     $certPath = $CertLocaton + "\" + $certName   
     $pfx.import($certPath,$pfxPass,"Exportable,PersistKeySet")    

     $store = new-object System.Security.Cryptography.X509Certificates.X509Store($certStore,$certRootStore)    
     $store.open("MaxAllowed")    
     $store.add($pfx)    
     $store.close()    
}
</code></pre>

<p>This makes certificate management easier. To manage certificates in this way, I just need to invoke a script similar to this:</p>

<pre><code>.\import-certificate.ps1 -CertificateName "mycert.pfx" -CertLocation "c:\ssl\mycerts"
</code></pre>

<p>Much simpler! You can download a <a href="https://gist.github.com/opentable-devops/5951108">gist</a> of this script should you wish to use it. Please note that the license that this script is available under can be read from our <a href="https://github.com/opentable/licensing/blob/master/LICENSE">github repository</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Windows Feature Management with PowerShell]]></title>
    <link href="http://tech.opentable.co.uk/blog/2013/06/14/windows-feature-management-with-powershell/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-14T20:31:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://tech.opentable.co.uk/blog/2013/06/14/windows-feature-management-with-powershell</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In late 2012, our development team started to move towards our systems being much more automated. Long gone are the days of developers creating runbooks in Word and giving them to our operations team to use to set up our production servers.</p>

<p>When building our webservers on Windows, in order to install / activate Windows features, this was the general set of instructions that was needed to be followed:</p>

<ul>
<li>Click Start Button</li>
<li>Click on Control Panel</li>
<li>Click on Programs</li>
<li>Click on Turn Windows features on or off</li>
</ul>


<p>This would present a screen as follows:</p>

<p>{% img center /images/posts/windowsfeature.png %}</p>

<p>You would need to find the correct features to enable and check the box, press OK and then wait for the features to be installed.</p>

<p>When Microsoft introduced Windows Server 2008 and PowerShell 2.0, they also introducted the module &lsquo;ServerManager&rsquo;. This is a module that allows us to interact, with PowerShell, Windows Features using a range of cmdlets:</p>

<ul>
<li>Get-WindowsFeature</li>
<li>Add-WindowsFeature</li>
<li>Remove-WindowsFeature</li>
</ul>


<p>This meant that instead of creating runbooks in Word, our developers could create automation scripts that would take a base Windows Server 2008 server and enable all the Windows Features needed to run our applications. This allowed our operations team to move much faster in configuring our servers.</p>

<p>To turn on the ASP.NET Application Development features in Windows, we would run the following script from PowerShell:</p>

<pre><code>Import-Module ServerManager
Add-WindowsFeature Web-Asp-Net
</code></pre>

<p>By knowing what Windows Features we needed to install on our servers, we were able to create the following script:</p>

<pre><code>function enable_net_3_5_features()
{
    Add-WindowsFeature NET-HTTP-Activation
    Add-WindowsFeature NET-Win-CFAC
    Add-WindowsFeature NET-Non-HTTP-Activ
    Add-WindowsFeature AS-MSMQ-Activation
}

function enable_iis_common_http_features()
{
    Add-WindowsFeature Web-Static-Content
    Add-WindowsFeature Web-Http-Errors
    Add-WindowsFeature Web-Default-Doc
}

function enable_iis_application_development_features()
{
    Add-WindowsFeature Web-Asp-Net
    Add-WindowsFeature Web-Net-Ext
    Add-WindowsFeature Web-ISAPI-Ext
    Add-WindowsFeature Web-ISAPI-Filter
}

function enable_iis_health_and_diagnostics_features()
{
    Add-WindowsFeature Web-Http-Logging
    Add-WindowsFeature Web-Request-Monitor
}

function enable_iis_security_features()
{
    Add-WindowsFeature Web-Filtering
}

function enable_iis_performance_features()
{
    Add-WindowsFeature Web-Stat-Compression
    Add-WindowsFeature Web-Dyn-Compression
}

function enable_iis_management_tools()
{
    Add-WindowsFeature Web-Mgmt-Tools
    Add-WindowsFeature Web-Mgmt-Console
}


Write-Host('Starting Application Server Setup')

Import-Module ServerManager
enable_net_3_5_features
enable_iis_common_http_features
enable_iis_application_development_features
enable_iis_health_and_diagnostics_features
enable_iis_security_features
enable_iis_performance_features
enable_iis_management_tools 

Write-Host('Application Server Setup complete')
</code></pre>

<p>Running the script, meant that we could enable features much faster than we could enable them via the GUI. Notice how we have grouped how we enable Windows Features into the same groupings found in the &lsquo;Turn Windows features on or off&rsquo; menu. For a full list of the names of the features that can be turned on or off, please refer to this <a href="http://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc732757.aspx">technet article</a></p>

<p>You can download a <a href="https://gist.github.com/opentable-devops/5886831">gist</a> of this script if you want to use it. Please note that the license that this script is available under can be read from our <a href="https://github.com/opentable/licensing/blob/master/LICENSE">github repository</a>. We hope that the script helps you as much as it helped us.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
