<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Microservices | OpenTable Tech UK Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://tech.opentable.co.uk/blog/categories/microservices/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://tech.opentable.co.uk/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-08T23:26:14+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://tech.opentable.co.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[OpenTable]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Proxying Services With Hapi.js]]></title>
    <link href="http://tech.opentable.co.uk/blog/2014/11/28/proxying-with-hapi/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-28T10:32:42+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://tech.opentable.co.uk/blog/2014/11/28/proxying-with-hapi</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve raved in the past about how awesome <a href="http://hapijs.com">hapi.js</a> is, but I&rsquo;m going to talk about just a specific case today.</p>

<p>We started off with just a couple of hapi.js apis. This was at a time when standing up new infrastructure was still a bit painful, so inevitably those apis ended up having more functionality in them than they should have. Now it&rsquo;s easy for us to get infrastructure, so we want to do more of it.</p>

<p>Our goal is to have lots of small(er) apis that just look after one specific piece (skillfully avoiding using the buzzword &lsquo;microservices&rsquo;).</p>

<p>When you want to split out functionality from one api to another, it can be a pain, especially if you have a lot of consumers who aren&rsquo;t particularly fast-moving or communicative. Or maybe you don&rsquo;t know all your consumers up front.</p>

<p>You&rsquo;ve got a couple of options here:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Maintain the functionality in two places and slowly migrate consumers across</p></li>
<li><p>Use a proxy or routing layer in-front of the api to rewrite or redirect requests</p></li>
<li><p>Write code in your api to proxy requests to a different server</p></li>
</ul>


<p>The first two options are pretty icky, and frankly the third isn&rsquo;t all that great either. It all depends on you having the right framework. Do you see where I&rsquo;m going here?</p>

<h3>Enter Hapi.js</h3>

<p>Hapi.js has the concept of a &lsquo;proxy&rsquo; handler, which can transparently proxy requests to a different server.</p>

<p>```javascript
server.route([
  {</p>

<pre><code>method: 'GET',
path: '/foo',
handler: {
  proxy: {
    host: 'my-other-service.mydomain.com',
    port: 80,
    protocol: 'http',
    passThrough: true,
    xforward: true
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>  }
]);
```</p>

<p>And boom, you&rsquo;re done. You can now safely delete <em>all</em> of that code from your api and move it. The <em>only</em> thing you need to have kicking about is that proxy handler code.</p>

<p>The <code>passthrough</code> setting specifies whether or not to preserve headers on the original request, and <code>xforward</code> tells hapi to add (or append) an &lsquo;x-forwarded-for&rsquo; header to the request.</p>

<p>The proxy handler is really powerful. It can rewrite the request (using <code>mapUri</code>), pass local-state (from the hapi instance) along, reject unauthorised requests, you can even hook into the response and monkey about with it if you want (using <code>onResponse</code>).</p>

<p>For full details, see the <a href="http://hapijs.com/api/v7.5.2#route-options">proxy section</a> of the route options.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
