<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: DevOps | OpenTable Tech UK Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://tech.opentable.co.uk/blog/categories/devops/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://tech.opentable.co.uk/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-26T10:26:59+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://tech.opentable.co.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[OpenTable]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Managing Windows Features with Puppet]]></title>
    <link href="http://tech.opentable.co.uk/blog/2014/05/15/managing-windows-features-with-puppet/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-15T16:12:38+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://tech.opentable.co.uk/blog/2014/05/15/managing-windows-features-with-puppet</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Back in June 2013, I wrote about <a href="http://tech.opentable.co.uk/blog/2013/06/14/windows-feature-management-with-powershell/">Windows Feature Management with PowerShell</a>. We have since released a Puppet module that will do this for us. We originally wrote PowerShell:</p>

<pre><code>Import-Module ServerManager
Add-WindowsFeature Web-Asp-Net
</code></pre>

<p>The Puppet module now wraps this code as follows:</p>

<pre><code>windowsfeature { 'Web-Asp-Net': }
</code></pre>

<p>The declaration windowsfeature is a specific Puppet type called a <a href="http://docs.puppetlabs.com/learning/definedtypes.html">define</a>. In developer terms, this is the equivalent of a helper method that can be reused. We can also make sure that Windows Features are <em>not</em> installed on the server as follows:</p>

<pre><code>windowsfeature { 'Telnet-Server': 
  ensure =&gt; absent 
}
</code></pre>

<p>In the backing code for the module, we do a check before we install / uninstall any windows features. This means that we will only make the changes we really need to. This ensures idempotency of the script. By using this class, we can build up a list of what features a server should have enabled / installed on it. As example manifest would look as follows:</p>

<pre><code>class my_windows_features {
  windowsfeature { 'Web-Asp-Net': }
  windowsfeature { 'Web-Net-Ext': }
  windowsfeature { 'Web-ISAPI-Ext': }
  windowsfeature { 'Web-ISAPI-Filter': }
  windowsfeature { 'Web-Mgmt-Tools': }
  windowsfeature { 'Web-Mgmt-Console': }
  windowsfeature { 'Telnet-Server': ensure =&gt; absent }
}
</code></pre>

<p>The server will have it&rsquo;s shipping list of Windows Features checked every 30 minutes by Puppet. We are sure that any changes encountered during that time will be applied as expected.  You can find more about our WindowsFeature module on the <a href="http://github.com/opentable/puppet-windowsfeature">github repo</a>. If you want to use the module, then you can install it using the Puppet Module tool via the <a href="http://forge.puppetlabs.com/opentable/windowsfeature">Puppet Forge</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Managing Windows Web Applications with Puppet]]></title>
    <link href="http://tech.opentable.co.uk/blog/2014/05/13/managing-windows-web-applications-with-puppet/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-13T15:25:16+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://tech.opentable.co.uk/blog/2014/05/13/managing-windows-web-applications-with-puppet</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As part of our move towards a configuration management tool, we really wanted to start automating as much of our infrastructure as possible. This included our application configuration stack. IIS management is pretty easy with PowerShell. It would look something like this</p>

<pre><code>Import-Module WebAdministration
New-WebSite -Name "DemoSite" -Port 80 -IP * -PhysicalPath "c:\inetpub\wwwroot" -ApplicationPool "MyAppPool"
</code></pre>

<p>This would of course set up a website called &lsquo;DemoSite&rsquo; running on port 80 on the local machine. The cmdlets that come with PowerShell make this pretty easy. This is great if it is a one-off job to set up a site. We run our websites from a number of webservers, therefore, it would be silly to have to RDP into each webserver and run a script on it. This is why tools like Puppet, Chef, Ansible etc. exist. We needed a configuration management tool to do this work for us. It has a number of benefits:</p>

<ul>
<li>Orchestration</li>
<li>Idempotency</li>
<li>Makes sure that each server is configured in &lsquo;exactly&rsquo; the same way as no human intervention is needed</li>
<li>Developers can help the operations team by creating the scripts needed. This is great for collaboration between teams</li>
</ul>


<p>On investigating how we would do this with Puppet, we noticed that there were not many other people managing their site in this way. Therefore, we would have to turn our PowerShell scripts into Puppet modules to manage our system.</p>

<p>We have since created a Puppet module to manage IIS. To manage IIS with Puppet, we can now write the following code:</p>

<pre><code>iis::manage_site { 'DemoSite:
   site_path     =&gt; 'c:\inetpub\wwwroot',
   port          =&gt; '80',
   ip_address    =&gt; '*',
   app_pool      =&gt; 'MyAppPool'
}
</code></pre>

<p>This would produce <strong>exactly</strong> the same results as the code from above. But it has 1 difference. There are checks in the code behind this module that will mean the code will only execute when it is needed, i.e. when the site_path isn&rsquo;t correct or the app_pool isn&rsquo;t correct. This is idempotency. The script can be run again and again and again&hellip;.</p>

<p>To create an application binding, we used to do this in PowerShell:</p>

<pre><code>Import-Module WebAdministration
New-WebBinding -Name 'DemoSite' -Port '8080' -IPAddress '*'
</code></pre>

<p>This would set up an extra binding on port 8080 for the site, DemoSite. We replaced this code with our puppet equivalent:</p>

<pre><code>iis::manage_binding { 'DemoSite-8080':
  site_name   =&gt; 'DemoSite',
  protocol    =&gt; 'http',
  port        =&gt; '8080',
  ip_address  =&gt; '*',
}
</code></pre>

<p>To create a virtual application, we would write the PowerShell:</p>

<pre><code>Import-Module WebAdministration
New-WebApplication -Name 'VirtualApp' -Site 'DemoSite' -PhysicalPath 'c:\inetpub\wwwroot\MyVirtualApp' -ApplicationPool 'MyAppPool'
</code></pre>

<p>This will create a VirtualApp folder on the DemoSite, use the same application pool and then set the path of the folder. I can do the same thing in Puppet as follows:</p>

<pre><code>iis::manage_virtual_application {'VirtualApp':
  site_name   =&gt; 'DemoSite',
  site_path   =&gt; 'C:\inetpub\wwwroot\MyVirtualApplication',
  app_pool    =&gt; 'MyAppPool'
 }  
</code></pre>

<p>We can therefore, chain a manifest together that does all this for us in 1 go. It would look as follows:</p>

<pre><code>class mywebsite {
  iis::manage_app_pool {'MyAppPool':
    enable_32_bit           =&gt; true,
    managed_runtime_version =&gt; 'v4.0',
  } -&gt;

  iis::manage_site {'DemoSite':
    site_path   =&gt; 'C:\inetpub\wwwroot',
    port        =&gt; '80',
    ip_address  =&gt; '*',
    app_pool    =&gt; 'MyAppPool'
  } -&gt;

  iis::manage_virtual_application {'VirtualApp':
    site_name  =&gt; 'DemoSite',
    site_path  =&gt; 'C:\inetpub\wwwroot\MyVirtualApp',
    app_pool   =&gt; 'MyAppPool'
  } -&gt; 

  iis::manage_binding {'DemoSite-8080':
    site_name  =&gt; 'DemoSite',
    protocol   =&gt; 'http',
    port       =&gt; '8080',
    ip_address =&gt; '*'
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>The module does more than just these tasks and I could give more and more examples of what we wrote, but you can find more about our IIS module on the <a href="http://github.com/opentable/puppet-iis">github repo</a>. If you want to use the module, then you can install it using the Puppet Module tool via the <a href="http://forge.puppetlabs.com/opentable/iis">Puppet forge</a>.</p>

<p>We love to hear feedback on things that the module should support. We like Pull Requests even more :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The adoption of Configuration Management]]></title>
    <link href="http://tech.opentable.co.uk/blog/2014/02/10/the-adoption-of-configuration-management/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-10T13:46:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://tech.opentable.co.uk/blog/2014/02/10/the-adoption-of-configuration-management</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In years gone by, we were a traditional IT company. We had teams of developers and operations. They rarely mixed. Around nine months ago we started to really try and get these teams working together. We introduced a configuration management tool, <a href="http://puppetlabs.com/puppet/what-is-puppet">Puppet</a>, into our ecosystem.</p>

<p>Configuration management is one of the steps of continuous delivery that developers often forget. They feel that systems are magically created for them to deploy their application to. I used to believe this. When I was focused on developing software, I never gave any thought as to the work our operations team had to do to keep the train on the track. So give some respect to your operations teams! We created a repository and started to experiment by configuring some of our applications using Puppet.</p>

<p>This was a major step for both sets of teams. The developers started being in charge of the configuration of their application. This meant that their application would guarantee to be configured the same in our CI environment as it was in production. We, as developers, would be more confident of our applications working as expected.</p>

<p>To contribute to the project, as an engineer, you need to:</p>

<ul>
<li>fork the project</li>
<li>make the changes you require</li>
<li>test the changes in a Vagrant environment (already created with a Windows and Linux system)</li>
<li>send a PR (pull request)</li>
</ul>


<p>We have just merged our #847 pull request. The stats of the repository look as follows:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/puppet-adoption.png"></p>

<p>Our puppet repository has had contributions from over 40% of our engineering / operations teams. We use Puppet to manage our application servers, DHCP servers, provisioning systems and even our MS Sql Server continuous integration infrastructure. The adoption has been fantastic. We started by running our internal QA infrastructure and then scaled it out to our production infrastructure. We now manage 548 nodes (a combination of internal and production) via Puppet.</p>

<p>Using a project called <a href="www.fullybaked.co.uk/articles/getting-gource-running-on-osx">Gource</a>, one of our engineering leads, <a href="http://twitter.com/ryantomlinson">Ryan Tomlinson</a>, created a video of the repository vizualization. It&rsquo;s just over two minutes long and shows the activity the repository has taken.</p>

<p><div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/86201508 "></iframe></div></p>

<p>Each branch in the tree relates to a directory inside our repository. Green zaps are additions, orange are updates and red deletions. The important thing to take from the video is the evolution of the repository, the amount of changes and the number of people pushing those changes.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m very happy with our configuration management adoption. We are by no means at a point where everyone does it, but we are working towards that. I would like our contributors to rise to over 75% of our engineering / operations team by the end of 2014. Let&rsquo;s see how that goes&hellip;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using Vagrant to work with ElasticSearch on your local machine]]></title>
    <link href="http://tech.opentable.co.uk/blog/2013/08/05/using-vagrant-to-work-with-elasticsearch-on-your-local-machine/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-05T08:45:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://tech.opentable.co.uk/blog/2013/08/05/using-vagrant-to-work-with-elasticsearch-on-your-local-machine</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently, I have started to work a lot more with <a href="http://www.vagrantup.com/">Vagrant</a> as a tool for creating a standard development environment across my team. This essentially means that regardless what the developers' machine is set up or running as, they can still reproduce the same environment as their colleagues just by entering a command.</p>

<p>Configuration managgement is something we have had to embrace to help us maintain an ever changing world of technologies. The hardest thing is knowing what we actually have to build in these environments. We use Vagrant to help us understand this. The simple flow is as follows:</p>

<ul>
<li>Developer starts a new project</li>
<li>Developer creates a Vagrantfile to spin up a local VM</li>
<li>Vagrantfile gets iterated on as the development process goes forward</li>
</ul>


<p>Once the developer understands what they need to actually run their software, we would then go about creating an environment to which this software will actually be deployed for end-to-end testing. I won&rsquo;t go any further into the details of our Vagrant flow in this post, if you want to read more about how to get started with Vagrant, then I would suggest reading <a href="http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920026358.do">Vagrant Up and Running</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/mitchellh">Mitchell Hashimoto</a>.</p>

<h2>Vagrant and ElasticSearch</h2>

<p>Whilst reviewing a book on <a href="http://www.elasticsearch.org/">ElasticSearch</a>, I noticed how simple the instructions were to get up and running with ElasticSearch. Please note, that there are already lots of Puppet modules for configuring ElasticSearch on <a href="http://forge.puppetlabs.com/modules?q=elasticsearch">Puppetlabs Forge</a>. This post only talks about how I was able to quickly spin up some local instances. I didn&rsquo;t want to manually do this, so I decided to use Vagrant (and Puppet) to take care of it for me. The instructions can be summarised as follows:</p>

<ul>
<li>Download and install the JavaSDK</li>
<li>Download the specific ElasticSearch package</li>
<li>Install ElasticSearch</li>
<li>Download and install curl (to be able to interact with ElasticSearch)</li>
<li>Make sure the service is started</li>
</ul>


<p>I hate doing this manually. Luckily, with the correct script, I am able to automate all of this as follows:</p>

<pre><code>Vagrant.configure("2") do |config|
    config.vm.box = "Ubuntu precise 64 VMWare"
    config.vm.box_url = "http://files.vagrantup.com/precise64_vmware.box"
    config.vm.network :forwarded_port, guest: 9200, host: 9200
    config.vm.provision :puppet do |puppet|
        puppet.module_path = '../setup/modules'
        puppet.manifests_path = '../setup/manifests'
        puppet.manifest_file = 'default.pp'
        puppet.options = '--verbose --debug'
    end
end
</code></pre>

<p>Essentially, this script says to create a clone of a VM from a predefined box, forward port 9200 on the vm to 9200 on my local machine and then provision the server using Puppet. The Puppet script works as follows:</p>

<pre><code>exec { "apt-get-update":
    command =&gt; "/usr/bin/apt-get update",
}

package {'curl':
    provider =&gt; apt,
    ensure   =&gt; latest,
    require  =&gt; Exec['apt-get-update']
}

class {'elasticsearch':
    version =&gt; '0.90.0',
    require =&gt; Exec['apt-get-update'],
}
</code></pre>

<p>This defines that the command apt-get-update gets applied (due to both the class and the package requiring it) and then will install curl and ElasticSearch in no particular order. Once the script runs, I will be able to open a browser on my local machine, go to <a href="http://localhost:9200">http://localhost:9200</a> and see the newly provisioned ElasticSearch node. The result of the JSON was something similar to this:</p>

<pre><code>{
    "ok" : true,
    "status" : 200,
    "name" : "Gibborim",
    "version" : {
        "number" : "0.90.0",
        "snapshot_build" : false,
    },
    "tagline" : "You Know, for Search"
}
</code></pre>

<p>By entering the URL, &lsquo;**<a href="http://localhost:9200/_cluster/health?pretty**">http://localhost:9200/_cluster/health?pretty**</a>&rsquo;, you can see the state of the ElasticSearch cluster. It should show something like this:</p>

<pre><code>{
    "cluster_name" : "elasticsearch",
    "status" : "yellow",
    "timed_out" : false,
    "number_of_nodes" : 1,              
    "number_of_data_nodes" : 1,         
    "active_primary_shards" : 5,        
    "active_shards" : 5,                
    "relocating_shards" : 0,            
    "initializing_shards" : 0,          
    "unassigned_shards" : 5             
}
</code></pre>

<p>I wanted to be able to provision multiple nodes and then let them create a cluster. I was able to take the existing Vagrantfile and then using the multi-environment features of Vagrant. This created a new Vagrantfile as follows:</p>

<pre><code>Vagrant::Config.run do |config|
    config.vm.box = "Ubuntu precise 64 VMWare"
    config.vm.box_url = "http://files.vagrantup.com/precise64_vmware.box"

    config.vm.define "es1" do |es1|
        es1.vm.network :hostonly, "192.168.1.10"
        es1.vm.provision :puppet do |puppet|
            puppet.module_path = '../setup/modules'
            puppet.manifests_path = '../setup/manifests'
            puppet.manifest_file = 'default.pp'
            puppet.options = '--verbose --debug'
        end
    end

    config.vm.define "es2" do |es2|
        es2.vm.network :hostonly, "192.168.1.11"
        es2.vm.provision :puppet do |puppet|
            puppet.module_path = '../setup/modules'
            puppet.manifests_path = '../setup/manifests'
            puppet.manifest_file = 'default.pp'
            puppet.options = '--verbose --debug'
        end
    end

    config.vm.define "es3" do |es3|
        es3.vm.network :hostonly, "192.168.1.12"
        es3.vm.provision :puppet do |puppet|
            puppet.module_path = '../setup/modules'
            puppet.manifests_path = '../setup/manifests'
            puppet.manifest_file = 'default.pp'
            puppet.options = '--verbose --debug'
        end
    end
end
</code></pre>

<p>This effectively tells Vagrant to create three instances of ElasticSearch using the Puppet configuration (as above). Each ElasticSearch node is given its own IP. Thanks to ElasticSearch using Multicast and Unicast discovery, it is able to find other nodes on the network and create a cluster. By running a similar url as before, &lsquo;**<a href="http://192.168.1.10:9200/_cluster/health?pretty**">http://192.168.1.10:9200/_cluster/health?pretty**</a>&rsquo;, we can now see that the cluster looks as follows:</p>

<pre><code>{
    "cluster_name" : "elasticsearch",
    "status" : "green",
    "timed_out" : false,
    "number_of_nodes" : 3,              
    "number_of_data_nodes" : 3,         
    "active_primary_shards" : 5,        
    "active_shards" : 15,                
    "relocating_shards" : 0,            
    "initializing_shards" : 0,          
    "unassigned_shards" : 0             
}
</code></pre>

<p>Using this method, we can continue to spin up as many instances as we need to replicate different scenarios or testing conditions. Vagrant has made this very easy to do. If you want a copy of the Vagrantfiles and Puppet modules to try this yourself, then you can find them on my <a href="https://github.com/stack72/vagrant-examples/tree/master/elasticsearch">github repository</a>. The scripts are available under the <a href="http://opensource.org/licenses/MIT">MIT</a> license.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Managing Windows Certificates with PowerShell]]></title>
    <link href="http://tech.opentable.co.uk/blog/2013/07/08/managing-windows-certificates-with-powershell/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-08T18:51:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://tech.opentable.co.uk/blog/2013/07/08/managing-windows-certificates-with-powershell</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Managing certificates on Windows is <em>really</em> painful. There is no easy way to do it. The general way to install a certificate to a Windows Server 2008 machine is as follows:</p>

<ul>
<li>Open the Certificates snap-in for a user, computer, or service.</li>
<li>In the console tree, click the logical store where you want to import the certificate.</li>
<li>On the Action menu, point to All Tasks, and then click Import to start the Certificate Import Wizard.</li>
<li>Type the file name containing the certificate to be imported.</li>
<li>If you want to specify where the certificate is stored, select Place all certificates in the following store, click Browse, and choose the certificate store to use. OR</li>
<li>If the certificate should be automatically placed in a certificate store based on the type of certificate, click Automatically select the certificate store based on the type of certificate.</li>
</ul>


<p>The first time I ran this process, I felt as though this was just wrong to not be able to automate. The goal of our team is to automate everything we are currently doing manually. PowerShell is a better option for this import process as it allows you to write code to do it. As we all know, code is better for a number of reasons, I won&rsquo;t go into the infrastructure as code argument in this post (but it is coming soon….). Using PowerShell, I can write a simple function as follows:</p>

<pre><code>function Import-PfxCertificate($certName, $CertLocaton, $certRootStore, $certStore) {    
     $pfx = new-object System.Security.Cryptography.X509Certificates.X509Certificate2    

     $pfxPass = convertto-securestring $CertPassword -asplaintext -force

     $certPath = $CertLocaton + "\" + $certName   
     $pfx.import($certPath,$pfxPass,"Exportable,PersistKeySet")    

     $store = new-object System.Security.Cryptography.X509Certificates.X509Store($certStore,$certRootStore)    
     $store.open("MaxAllowed")    
     $store.add($pfx)    
     $store.close()    
}
</code></pre>

<p>This makes certificate management easier. To manage certificates in this way, I just need to invoke a script similar to this:</p>

<pre><code>.\import-certificate.ps1 -CertificateName "mycert.pfx" -CertLocation "c:\ssl\mycerts"
</code></pre>

<p>Much simpler! You can download a <a href="https://gist.github.com/opentable-devops/5951108">gist</a> of this script should you wish to use it. Please note that the license that this script is available under can be read from our <a href="https://github.com/opentable/licensing/blob/master/LICENSE">github repository</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
